Guide to the James S. Allen Papers TAM.142
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series V: Subject Files, 13381
  - Farm Trip Midwest (see also: box 3, folder 9A), 1932; 13411 (Box 3, Folder 29A)
  - 50th Anniversary (Russian Revolution), 1967; 13410 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Gates Revisionism, 1956-1960; 13409 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Imperialism - Colonialism, 1948, 1957-1959; 13408 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Japan, 1970, undated; 13407 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Japan: Photographs, March 1970; 544703; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Latin America, undated; 13406 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Marx, Karl - "Accumulation of Capital and Crisis" (Issued by the National Education Department, CPUSA), undated; 13405 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Marx - Engels, Collected Works, undated; 13404 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Marx - Engels, Collected Works: Condition of the Working Class in England, undated; 13403 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Middle Strata, ca.1956-1957; 13402 (Box 4, Folder 1A)
  - Moscow, Trip, 1974; 13401 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pacific Relations, Institute of, 1952, 1959; 13400 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Peaceful Coexistence, Transition, etc., 1958-1959; 13399 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Poland Land Program, undated; 13398 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Romania, Summer Trip (Includes Journal), 1971-1972; 13397 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Scottsboro, Decatur Trial, 1933; 13396 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Socialism and Communism: Marx, Lenin, and Stalin on Theory, undated; 13395 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Groups, Parties, and Trends, 1956-1958; 13394 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Spanish Civil War/Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1937-1939, circa 1974; 544704; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Stages - Anti-Monopoly and Socialism (Notes), ca.1957-1959; 13393 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Southern Worker: Clippings, 1930-1931; 13392 (Box 4, Folder 10A)
  - Technology and Social Change, undated; 13391 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Temporary National Economic Committee (TNEC), 1940-1941; 13390 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Twelve Party Declaration, 1957-1959; 13389 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Unemployment, Summary Discussion of (CP National Economic Committee Meeting); 9-10 Mar 1961., 13388 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - US Economy - General Movement, 1955-1959; 13387 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - US Foreign Investment (Post WWII), ca.1958; 13386 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - USSR, GDR, and Czechoslovakia Trip Journals, 1960-1961; 13385 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - USSR, Trip Journals, 1960-1961; 13384 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - USSR, Trip to, 1960-1961, 1974; 13383 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - USSR, Trip to - Notes, Sketches, and Letters Home, 1927; 13382 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series VI: Writings, 13275
  The Writings series contains manuscripts and typescripts of unpublished, and some published works, in some cases along with relevant correspondence, notes and research materials, and is organized into four subseries.
  - Subseries A: Negro Question in the United States, 13366
    Subseries A: The Negro Question in the U.S. contains book reviews, post-WWII Black Belt statistical data and calculations, a partial typescript for a proposed revised edition, several unpublished essays from the 1950s, CP Negro Commission meeting notes and reports by Allen, James Jackson, and Doxey Wilkerson, and the proceedings of a 1956 Conference on The South, organized by the Jefferson School.
    - Black Belt Calculations, 1950; 13380 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Black Belt Statistics, 1950, 1970; 13379 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Census Material, 1948, 1970-1972; 13378 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence re: Negro Question in the United States, 1949, 1971; 13377 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Communist Party National Committee and Negro Commission: Discussion on Negro Question (Includes Notes and Reports by Allen, James Jackson, and Doxey Wilkerson), 1956-1958; 13376 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Jackson, James E: Black Belt, Negro Question - Communist Party Internal Reports, 1951-1956, undated; 13375 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Negro Question, Essays on the, 1956-1959; 13374 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Negro Question in the US: Partial Typescript for a Proposed Post-WWII (Revised) Edition, ca.1946; 13373 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Negro Question in the US: Preface to Revised Edition, ca.1947; 13372 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - New Material for Negro Question in the US, 1949, undated; 13371 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Reviews of the Negro Question in the US, 1936-1937; 13370 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - The South, Conference on (Jefferson School of Social Science; 30-Jun 1956, 13369 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Theoretical Aspects of the Negro Question in the US; Feb-1959, 13368 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Subseries B: Organizing in the Depression South, 13355
    Subseries B: Organizing in the Depression South contains a partial typescript of this work.
    - Contents, undated; 13365 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - II: We Go South, undated; 13364 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - III: Founding the Southern Worker, undated; 13363 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - IV: The Beginning of Communist Organization, undated; 13362 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - V: Tallapoosa, undated; 13361 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - VI: Scottsboro, undated; 13360 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - VII: The Decatur Trial, undated; 13359 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - VIII: Epilogue (re: Scottsboro), undated; 13358 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Appendix I: Foster, William Z. "The Worker's (Communist) Party in the South", undated; 13357 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Appendix II: Documents, undated; 13356 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subseries C: Visions and Revisions, 13344
    Subseries C: "Visions and Revisions," contains chapters on Allen's early years, travels to the Philippines and the Soviet Union, and his publishing career from his unpublished autobiographical typescript. The partial typescript in Subseries B was originally written as part of "Visions and Revisions."
    - Visions and Revisions Book One: Table of Contents, undated; 13354 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - I: The Young Years, undated; 13353 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - II: Generations, undated; 13352 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - III: The Soviet Union, 1927, undated; 13351 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - IV: New York and Cleveland, undated; 13350 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - IX: Black Self-Determination, undated; 13349 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - X: Dialectics of Liberation ("Black Liberation"), undated; 13348 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - XI: The Philippines {See also: Series IV: Philippines}, undated; 13347 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - XII: The Philippines Revisited, undated; 13346 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - XVIII: Marxist Publisher, undated; 13345 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Subseries D: Other, 13276
    Subseries D: Other Writings contains numerous brief, mostly unpublished typescripts from the late 1920s through the early 1980s. Many deal with the debates over Party policy and theory in the 1945-1960 era (critiques of Earl Browder and John Gates); others cover various topics including current events, political economy, the Soviet Union, and the developing countries, including an interview with the former leader of the Cuban Communist Party, Blas Roca (1978). There are also book contracts and reviews, memorial portraits of prominent communists, and publishing correspondence for American Communism and Black Americans (1987), Atomic Imperialism (1952), Reconstruction (1937), and The Radical Left on the Eve of War (1985). There is also correspondence pertaining to Allen's publications written after Allen's death by his sons and his collaborators, particularly Robin G. D. Kelley, who worked on Allen's manuscript, "Communism in the Deep South," later published as Organizing in the Depression South: A Communist's Memoir (2001).
    - American Communism and Black Americans: Correspondence, 1983-1985; 13343 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - American Foreign Investment, 1949, 1958; 13342 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - American History, Essays on, ca.1937, 1954; 13341 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Atomic Energy and Society (Letter signed by Albert Einstein), 1949-1950; 13340 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Atomic Imperialism: Correspondence and Reviews, 1950-1952, 1954; 13339 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Atomic Imperialism: Raw Materials, 1938, 1948-1950; 13338 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Book Contracts, 1946-1962; 13337 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Book Project, 1958-1960; 13336 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Book Reviews by Allen, undated; 13335 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Browder's Utopian World (Submitted to Political Affairs - Rejected), 1948; 13334 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Changing Position of American Capitalism in the World Economy During WWII; Main Characteristics of the Economy of WWII (Unpublished Transcripts and Correspondence), 1948-1949; 13333 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Communist Party USA - Reviews (typescript) of Various Books, undated; 13332 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence re: Publications, 1984-1994; 544698; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - The Crisis of Foreign Policy (Report on Behalf of CPUSA Foreign Affairs Committee); 24-Oct 1957, 13331 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Cuba: Interview with Blas Roca; 4 - 13 Apr 1978, 13330 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Detente, 1973; 13329 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Did the CEC Prepare the Party for May Day, ca.1929; 13328 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Early Unpublished Writing, 1928-1935; 13327 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Economic Cycles, 1948-1956; 13326 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Eisenhower Monopoly Government, 1952-1953; 13325 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - The Eisenhower Monopoly Government (Rejected by Political Affairs), 1953; 13324 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Elections - Truman Government, 1948-1952; 13323 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Electoral Strategy, 1958; 13322 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Foreign Affairs: Notes and Typescripts, 1945-1948; 13321 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Foreign Policy, 1949-1960; 13320 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hungary, Communist Party in, 1956-1957; 13319 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - India, 1942, undated; 13318 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Kelley, Robin D. G.: Manuscript and Published Article, circa 1988-1990; 544699; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - Kennedy and the Berlin Crisis (Nuclear Testing), ca.1961; 13317 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "The Charles H. Kerr Company Archives, 1885-1985: A Century of Socialist and Labor Publishing," ed. Franklin Rosemont, circa 1985; 544700; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - Lenin - National Question, undated; 13316 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The Making of a Communist Intellectual: Notes for a Chapter, undated; 13315 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Marx - National Question, undated; 13314 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Memoirs, 1973-1980; 13313 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mexico, Crisis in, ca.1940-1942; 13312 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous: Unpublished Brief Typescripts 1940s - 1950s, 1940-1960; 13311 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous: Unpublished Brief Typescripts (By Title) 1960s - 1980s, 1960-1990; 13310 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Monopoly Capital in the United States (A Preliminary Prospectus for a New Book), undated; 13309 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Monopoly, Notes for, 1941-1946, 1953; 13308 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - National Farm Conference, 1940; 13307 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Nazi - Soviet Pact, 1939, 1984; 13306 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - The Need for a Critical "New Look" (Discussion Article); Note to Dennis and Foster re: Its Rejection for Publication in the Daily Worker, by John Gates; Mar - Apr 1956, 13305 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "The Negro Question: A Discussion" - Article, Political Affairs; Nov-1946, 1946-11; 13304 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Neo - Colonialism, 1970-1971; 13303 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Notes for Later Autobiography: Materials for XIII, undated; 13302 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Party Crisis: Notes and Comments JSA, 1956; 13301 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Party in Different Socialist Societies, 1971; 13300 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Party Report for Chapter XIII, 1939-1977; 13299 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Portraits (Brief): Gerhard Eisler, Brit Burt, and Ruth Shaw, undated; 13298 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Political Economy - Various Notes and Reviews, 1977, 1983-1984; 13297 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Problem of "Independent" Communist Parties, 1985; 13296 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Reconstruction: Correspondence, 1937-1938, 1948; 13295 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Reconstruction: Notes, 1955; 13294 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Reconstruction: The Battle for Democracy (Reviews), 1937-1938; 13293 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Revisionism, 1957-1960; 13292 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Rochester, Anna, 1966; 13291 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Role of Tradition in History, undated; 13290 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - South, Notes, 1984; 13289 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Soviet - Chinese Relations, 1984-1985; 13288 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Soviet Society in History, the Place of, 1964; 13287 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - State Monopoly Capitalism, ca.1959-1960; 13286 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Taxi, Mister and Other Writing, 1927; 13285 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Teheran: Various Views of the Browder Episode, undated; 13284 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Trade Associations, undated; 13283 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Unpublished Writings, 1939-1941; 13282 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Unpublished Writings (War), 1939-1945; 13281 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Unpublished Writings, 1945-1947; 13280 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - USSR Attitude to: Reflections, 1976-1977; 13279 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Welfare State: (Bittelman, Alexander), 1957-1960; 13278 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - World Monopoly and Peace Controversy, 1946-1948; 13277 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Scrapbooks and Charts, 13263
  The last series consists of photocopies of six thick scrapbooks, and three sets of oversized charts. The first four scrapbooks contain Allen's articles in the Communist press, almost all from the Daily Worker and The Communist/Political Affairs (1928-1967), the fifth contains reviews of his books (1936-1962), and the last commemorates his 60th birthday. The charts contain Black Belt county population data, 1860-1950, and were compiled by Allen from U.S. Census figures.
  - Subseries A: Scrapbooks, 13268
    - Scrapbook 1: Articles by Allen - Newspaper & Periodicals, 1928-1939; 13274 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook 2: Articles by Allen - Newspaper 1941-Mar 1944, 1941-1944; 13273 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook 3:Articles by Allen - Newspaper; Oct. 1944-1947, 13272 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook 4: Articles by Allen - Periodicals, 1940-1967; 13271 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook 5: Reviews of Allen's Books, 1936-1962; 13270 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook 6: Sixtieth Birthday, 1966; 13269 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subseries A: Charts, 13264
    - Black Belt County Population Data - Set 1, 1860, 1910-1930; 13267 (Flat-file 1, Drawer 5, Folder 1)
    - Black Belt County Population Data - Set 2, 1870-1900; 13266 (Flat-file 1, Drawer 5, Folder 2)
    - Black Belt County Population Data - Set 3, 1940-1950; 13265 (Flat-file 1, Drawer 5, Folder 1)